A Guide to the Minutes of the Virginia Board of Medical Assistance Services, 1965-1999
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Minutes of the Virginia Board of Medical Assistance Services, 1965-1999
The Library of Virginia
36063, 43303
11 cu. ft. (11 boxes)
Virginia. Board of Medical Assistance Services
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred on 21 October 1998 from the Virginia Board of Medical Assistance Services, 600 E. Broad St., Suite 1300, Richmond, VA. [Acc. 36063]
Transferred on 2 July 2007 from the Virginia Board of Medical Assistance Services, 600 E. Broad St., Suite 1300, Richmond, VA. [Acc. 43303]
Biographical Information
In 1965 President Johnson signed into law a bill creating the Medicare and Medicaid programs of the Social Security Act. The following year the General Assembly authorized the development of a medical assistance program (Medicaid) to provide comprehensive health care services to Virginia's poor. Virginia's Medicaid program became operational in 1969 under the Dept. of Health and in 1985 a separate organization entity, the Dept. of Medical Assistance Services, was created to administer the program, which was the sole function of the DMAS until 1989.
The mission of the Dept. of Medical Assistance Services is to provide information, expertise and policy recommendations that enable policy makers to plan for the provision of indigent health care services and to administer the financing of health care services to ensure access to those services for eligible persons within applicable laws and available sources. The Department strives to ensure that the categorically and medically needy citizens of the Commonwealth have financial access to cost effective, comprehensive health care delivery systems by administering the following: Medicaid program, Indigent Health Care Trust Fund, State and Local Hospital Program, Involuntary Commitment Program, Regular Assisted Living Payment for Residents of Adult Homes, Health Premium Assistance Program for HIV-positive Individuals, and the Virginia Children's Medical Security Insurance Plan Trust Fund. The Department also ensures that services are medically necessary and of acceptable quality and that services and payments are in compliance with state, federal and program regulations.
Scope and Content
Minutes and related attachments, 1965-1999, documenting the activities and decisions of the Virginia Board of Medical Assistance Services. Also includes correspondence, memoranda, and reports.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into two series.
Series I: Minutes, 1965-1996 [Acc. 36063]
Series II: Minutes, 1996-1999 [Acc. 43303]
Contents List
- Series I: Minutes, 1965-1996 [Acc. 36063]., Extent: 9 cu. ft. [9 boxes]. (Box 1-9)
  - Minutes, 1985-1988 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 1990-1992 (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - Minutes, 1993-1995 (Box 5)
  - Minutes, 1995-1996 (Box 6)
  - Minutes, 1982-1988 (Box 7)
  - Minutes, 1989-1991 (Box 8)
  - Minutes, 1965-1988; 1991-1993 (Box 9)
- Series II: Minutes, 1996-1999 [Acc. 43303]., Extent: 2 cu. ft. [2 boxes]. (Box 1-2)
  - Minutes, 1996-1997 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1997-1999 (Box 2)